- Welcome, welcome, welcome.
For the last panel actually of the today event,
very, very excited to be here with you guys to close us off.
Really, we're gonna talk,
Sebastian is on his way, he's getting miked up in the back.
Really over the next couple of minutes,
our goal is to talk about the big trends to watch
for the next 12 months.
We're gonna cover a whole multitude of developments.
I can promise you it's gonna be insightful,
interesting, and hopefully exciting as well.
This episode is powered by Zappobank.
Experience the future of banking with Zappobank,
the first fully licensed
and regulated Bitcoin enabled banking group.
With Zappobank's all in one app,
you can grow, transact, and secure your Bitcoin.
Earn annual Bitcoin yield paid daily
on your Bitcoin and US dollar savings,
plus cash back on your card spending.
Or instantly send and receive Bitcoin
with the Lightning Network
and seamlessly transact in USDC, USDT, US dollars,
euros, and pounds.
All this is backed by rock solid security,
including military-grade Swiss bunkers,
cutting edge digital protocols,
and strict regulatory oversight.
Sign up now at zappobank.com/capsule,
or check the link in the episode description.
This episode is brought to you by ACX Compliance,
your one-stop shop for all your crypto compliance needs
in the UAE and beyond.
From Vara licensing support,
to crypto compliance training and customized support,
including crypto specialized transaction monitoring,
and SAR reporting filing support.
ACX Compliance has over 200 crypto compliance professionals
that are 100% training crypto
and 100% focused on the crypto industry.
If you're looking for a one-stop shop
to really help you with all your crypto compliance needs,
take ACX Compliance.
Find out more at www.accompliance.com.
- And because we are the dream team today,
we have Alex Rafus is next to me, the CEO of Chillies.
One thing, by the way, you may not know about Alex.
Literally, he runs Chillies,
socials, like a sports fine club platform,
but he's not a big sports fan.
Believe it or not, he's a tech fan,
which never ceases to amaze me.
Great to have you, Alex.
And of course, Justin Son, the founder of Tron,
who's also with us today.
Interesting, by the way,
with Justin just recorded the new Tron Anton with Hans Zimmer.
So here we go, a new first in the industry
and Sebastian is joining us as well.
In a second, Sebastian, by the way, many may not know.
He's an avid collector of Japanese comic books, by the way.
So that's another interesting thing with Sebastian.
Guys, let's kick it off.
We're gonna cover a lot of topics today.
I'm gonna jump right in.
So I'm gonna, there you go, Sebastian is here.
- What an entrance for me. - Sorry for being here.
- How are you? - How are you?
I thought you got lost in the sandbox metaverse.
- I was in the metaverse and right here with you now.
- Here we go, here we go.
I was telling you about how you're an avid comic book
collector, Sebastian.
So guys, let me give you guys how it's gonna roll.
I'm gonna, we're gonna talk about
really the entire sort of topics today.
As I start, I wanna number from one to 10,
whether you're bullish on it or not.
One, you're not bullish, 10, you're super bullish,
on whatever I'm gonna talk about, okay?
Ready?
Let's kick it off.
The first one, stablecoins.
We saw a great presentation earlier about
what's happening on the tether side.
How bullish are you for the growth of the stablecoin ecosystem
from one to 10 for the next year?
- I'm massively bullish that it will stay $1.
- Okay, one to 10, one to 10.
- 10, 10.
- 10, Justin, nine.
Nine.
Justin, why are you so bullish on, what are you watching
for the year to come on the stablecoin side?
- Yes, I feel like stablecoin payment and mass adoption
is one of the most important use cases actually
being used by people outside of the blockchain world, right?
So we have like DeFi, NFT,
like Bitcoin layer two solution, like re-staking,
but most of them, people outside of the creative world
have no idea on what's going on, right?
Didn't you keep tracking on all the new terms?
But they just want to use like stablecoin as a payment
which is fast, cheap, and instant transaction.
So that's a use case, only use case I think in our industry.
The people outside of the crypto world can understand
and they can start you from the stablecoin
start you gradually on board
onto all the crypto infrastructure.
- And actually the data we saw today from parallel
from the tether was very impressive actually,
how much the growth is happening,
but I think a lot going on.
Second topic, the metaverse, this is Sebastian's favorite,
how bullish are you for the year to come one to 10?
- Oh, that's unfair, six and a half.
- Six and a half, Justin?
- Eight. - All right.
- Sebastian, how bullish are you next year?
- 10. - Well.
- So let's start with you, of course,
I'm not surprised you're a 10 on this.
So what are you watching?
Obviously there's a lot going on with the sandbox,
but what should we watch in the next 12 months
in the broader metaverse ecosystems?
- So looking at a few things,
one is really the growth of the creator economy,
like now I'm boarding more and more people
to become credit to make experiences.
We just passed a thousand experiences live on sandbox
in a matter of few months.
So anyone can start building experiences
without any knowledge, thanks to AI,
thanks to like no-code tools, can publish an experience.
We're working on the ground in different region of the world
to onboard them to one of the most concrete use cases,
through gaming and through the usual generated content,
to the use of blockchain technology,
to make people feel like what they create these areas
can be used where they want, can be monetized,
and the asset they own can also be utilized somewhere
in other applications.
That's one exciting thing.
Also the metaverse has this power to bring us together
through culture, onboarding a lot of brands,
from music, from sport, for entertainment.
So it's a very intuitive use case as well,
and it's driving a lot of engagement, a lot of loyalty.
People enjoy exploring, people enjoy getting rewards.
Their time is actually very valued
in the space.
And I think it's here, like there's no denial.
Like metaverse is far from that, it's active.
People are building, we're building it together,
and it will keep growing from the years to go.
- So Sebastian mentioned engagement in sports.
I have to ask you, like what, obviously there's a lot of people,
I'm sure they're into sports here,
on the fan, token side, and broader sports engagement.
What should we watch for the next 12 months?
- I think in our case, it's mainly about the utility
of the tokens.
We've been very lucky for the last six years
in building this fan token economy,
and we work with like 80 sports team,
and these teams have to provide more to their fans.
Right now, we are still very early stage,
and we are trying to brand these sports-fi,
you have DeFi, game-fi, sport-fi,
is the next generation or the next vertical
we are going to try to promote.
And again, these football teams,
these legacy brands, as I like to call them,
they have, I'm not gonna say hundreds of millions of fans,
but they do have thousands of millions of fans.
But these fans are not customers.
So the question is, how do you translate a fan
to a consumer, and I think web3/web2.5,
as I would like to say sometimes, is the right path.
- Really the question, the creator economy.
Sebastian mentioned the creator economy.
- The economy, the creator.
- What's up from Sebastian this time?
How old are you? - 15.
- 20. - 20.
- 20, eight. - Eight?
- Eight, he's a fair one.
- Yeah.
- Tell me more, so let me start from you on, Sebastian.
Why this creator economy?
Then I'm gonna move to you just, yes.
- I think it's essential, like any one of us
can become a creator, and there's no future of gaming
where the players are not contributor.
And extending that beyond gaming,
I feel like participating, creating content,
being engaged in community,
having our own social token and going further,
it's all the ultimate form of engagement
that we're looking for, and so like we need to provide the tool,
the technology to empower the people to become creator.
Like against AI, like allowing people to be more creative
is actually the only way forward for humanity, I would say,
that will keep us like really distinguished
from robots and machines.
So yeah, I think that's super bullish
on the creator economy.
- Justin, are you as bullish as Sebastian or a bit less?
- Yes, for creator economy actually,
for most of people who don't know,
I developed like a live streaming platform
actually, you know, 10 years ago.
It's actually have lots of creators on my platform.
We take also a very big commission on the contribution.
So at that time I started to feel like the Apple Tax
and the Google Play Tax is so high.
It's imposed basically 30% on the older contribution.
So that's why I really believe Blockchain
has this kind of the way to democratize the creator economy.
You really empower the creator to create content,
and at the same time they can get much more
compared to the web two days.
- Yeah, it's very, very interesting, actually,
that's a really little bit to the creator economy, meme coins.
I mean, there's a lot of controversy around meme coins.
You believe that it will have a growth,
how big will be the growth of meme coins in the year to come?
One to 10.
- Oh, again, I'm the bad cop, always.
Well, actually eight.
- Eight, Justin.
- Meme coin, 10th, 10th.
- Wow, 10th, same 10th, it's cultural.
- What do you think to Justin?
Why do you think you're so bullish on them?
- Yeah, sure, first of all,
I believe Meme coin is the first thing in our industry.
Differentially, ourself from traditional industry, right?
Because, you know, we have like Shiba, like Loki,
like all different kinds of the animals.
Like, valuation is like about like 10 billion dollars, right?
Which like traditional finance guy
would feels like make no sense, right?
But I think behind the 10 billion valuation
is the community engagement, like Fair launch,
you know, community participation.
Actually, I think Craig, a very successful Meme coin,
it's just as hard as Craig, a good crypto project, right?
That's also one of the reasons why, like Elon Musk,
like keep endorsing dodgy coin,
I think because doge actually is one of the top,
like crypto brand, I would say.
So that's why I think in every cycle,
it will have new Meme token, right?
Doge coin is back to 2014, and then we have Shiba.
I think for the next bull's cycles,
we will see other Meme coin.
But consider the limitation of the animals here.
We won't have too much of the small one.
We never know, there's a lot of creativity in the industry.
But it's incredible, Justin, as well,
the number of people I mean in crypto
where the first entry to the space
has been by Meme coins from Doge coin to others.
Very interesting.
I know you want to add to this, Alex.
Yeah, what is a Meme coin?
It's actually a community that tokenized their community.
So when you think you're going to promote Fan Token,
but a Fan Token is a tokenization of a community
related to a legacy brand, Paris and German,
FC Barcelona, et cetera.
A Meme coin is the same, except that the brand
that you're supporting or the community
that you're supporting is new.
And that's very interesting.
And in crypto, we've seen in the last 10 years
that organic/native communities are actually more powerful
that usually traditional brand.
And even for us, it's a challenge.
As an entrepreneur in that space, I hate it, Meme coins.
We have 300 employees, and our job
is to try to bring utility to crypto and blockchain.
And then you see these things happening,
and they are very successful.
It is frustrating.
But then you have a way to embrace it.
You have a way to embrace it because it does create a awareness
to blockchain, to crypto.
People want fun.
Well, you know what? You have to give people what they want.
I always say, it's like, how do you put a value
to a Reddit community, right?
I think that's what a lot of these token memes are doing.
Next one, AI in crypto.
How much activity do you space in the conversions of AI in crypto?
I just want to start from Sebastian.
I'm giving you a break.
AI in crypto, Sebastian.
Nine.
Nine?
Justin?
Ten, of course, ten.
No, no, no, half.
Even though I have no idea why.
Just because I don't want to be a black duck on the street.
Justin, why do you think?
What's exciting about that?
Yeah, sure.
First of all, I believe AI is a very powerful technology.
I actually use lots of technology.
Please go on the Twitter and the YouTube of Justin
to see how AI is used because you will see him talking
in English very differently than how it is right now.
And it's fascinating.
What's wrong with his English?
You know, look at me, I'm French.
Yeah, exactly.
Yes, so I think AI is very powerful, too.
You can create lots of things.
And also, I recently been obsessed with robots.
So I have, like, a robot dog.
I also share on the social media.
So I put in some calls and a program with my robot dog.
I actually can't do lots of things.
So that's why I believe AI is very powerful tools.
And recently, I started to realize I also
read something about the robot dogs.
I'm considering if my robot dog is controlled by other person
and tried to rob me.
And then they can just give me a big coin or, like,
strong, like, QR code.
Tell me to send the USDT or big coin to the robot dog.
Or he did something bad for me, right?
So I think the combination with AI and blockchain
will have a big potential.
Because once, if we enable robots with money
with financial services, they can do, like, whatever,
you ask them to do.
Especially if it's happening behind the scenes as well, right?
It could be on it.
This is going to be, I think, Sebastian's favorite.
Gaming and crypto.
What are you guys watching?
Gaming crypto.
Sebastian, from 1 to 10.
10.
Not surprised.
Justin?
10.
42, because it's the answer to everything.
Sebastian, what are you watching?
I know you've even before sandbox.
You spend a lot of years in the gaming world.
Yeah, so I'm also, like, present of the blockchain
game alliance.
Here we go.
We're in a growing association that now
counts over 600 members.
Really excited to think, like, we're
still into a very early and experimental phase
of, like, how blockchain and decentralization
can be used in gaming mechanics.
Like, we've seen, like, now, like,
free drop of NFT, such as game characters, equipment,
to onboard community, into games.
We've seen new mechanics that touch around, like,
decentralized finance, as well, like, you need to stake
certain of your cryptocurrency to be
able to access, like, certain content and NFTs.
We've seen everything from traditional gaming and eSport,
like Battle Pass, leaderboard, competition.
And now it goes as far as, like, touching areas of, like,
Twitch and contributor of live streaming
and also platform around prediction gaming, as well,
and competitive eSport.
So essentially, I believe, like, the technology here,
blockchain and NFT crypto is essentially
contributing to redistribute the value between all the actors
of the value chain within the gaming
and even creating more jobs with guilds,
with content contributor, with the creator economy, as well.
So it's very powerful marriage that's, like,
going to change the whole gaming industry.
Specifically, as it is very challenged right now,
if you look at web2 and free to play,
the traditional equation, which is, like,
CPI versus cell TV, like, how much a user costs
to acquire versus how much you generate revenue from
by selling in a purchase ads, et cetera,
is at the worst moment ever in that 15 years longer industry.
Why is because, like, privacy laws have forced,
like the platform, to stop collecting data
on how users are behaving.
So you cannot target users any more properly.
So the CPI is rising.
And the current economical context of the world
with inflation has made that people are spending less
and less in entertainment.
So LTV is decreasing.
That has led this year, I think, in 2024,
massive layoff around, like, the whole gaming industry,
post-COVID, 25% of large companies,
even including Unreal, Unity, et cetera, have been laid off.
So it's the time to reinvent.
It's challenging, but it's also an opportunity
to rethink the model that we've sustained for so long.
- Very interesting.
When it comes to gaming, but obviously, it's an e-sports,
for example, are you seeing this conversion?
- I'm not definition of an expert like Sebastian.
So e-sports is a bit of a different animal,
because e-sports is a way where you watch games
and watch competitions.
We do work as a company, or as a chain event.
We work with six or seven of the biggest e-sports team
in the world, and because we are between friends here,
it's very difficult.
Why?
Because fans of e-sports teams, they are very fragmented.
They are not high-spenders.
They are very dedicated to the games' death support.
They are not very big fans of crypto,
probably because we haven't collectively provided
the right product yet, but it's a very difficult space.
So we've been more successful in traditional sports,
ironically, actually, if you look at the white paper
of Chile's in 2018, when we launched the first two years,
we were going to focus on e-sports.
I can tell you, after three months, we changed everything.
We said, no, no, we're going to focus in traditional sports,
because it's much more global.
And the sports company, as entities,
are easier to work than with e-sports company, ironically.
Interesting, wow.
Next one.
NFTs are a tough year this year.
NFTs, how bullish are you on NFTs for the year today?
It's very unfair again.
We start from you, Alex.
NFTs are tech.
It's not a product, so as a tech 10,
the question is which product?
Justin.
I would say, eight.
Eight.
Ten.
Ten as well.
Why do I say it's a basket?
Well, I think NFTs are more a store of culture.
We only see the first iteration of what NFT can represent,
whether it's art, collectible sport asset, gaming asset,
like avatar, virtual land, or content made by creators.
But there's a lot of updates around dynamic NFT,
around technologies, like a counter abstraction
that allows to basically make an NFT a container that
includes its own logic with built-in smart contract
and segregation of--
so it's going to become, ultimately,
keep evolving and allows new form of interaction.
Also, the overall blockchain gaming industry
is so nascent that it's still a lot of use cases
to be derived from the use of NFTs.
Interpability is a great concept, but so few games
have really varied it so far for user acquisition and more.
And even everything touching to real-world assets,
I'm sure there's a lot of different asset classes
that haven't yet been tokenized.
And whether they will be tokenized in a fungible or non-fungible
form, that's a lot of opportunities.
You mentioned acquisitions.
Let's talk about M&A, and we see we're entering in a bull market.
What's you guys view on M&A and fundraising
the crypto space?
I start from you, Sebastian.
M&A in the crypto space.
6.
Wow, interesting.
Justin.
10.
10, as well.
Alex.
12.
Why are you 12?
I do believe there is--
and I've been public on this, so that's why.
I do believe there is already too many tokens.
There is too many every day.
There is a new layer, one layer, two ZK, something, whatever.
And so there is a lot of VC money behind it,
because they are washing their money and cycles,
and every cycle, it works so good for them.
But from a token perspective, which, at least as issuer
and as platforms, it does matter, the more tokens,
the less liquidity, the more it's fragmented.
And I think one of the next big things in the next 12 months
will be token M&A. And when I said token M&A,
I'm not talking about corporate M&A,
where two companies will merge.
I'm talking, really, companies merging their token
to either one new one or old one,
and working on the semicol system, working on the same platform,
actually having aligned interest and trying to grow that ladder
and creating, I will call that, not a meta token,
but a super token, where you have all of these token aggregated.
I'm a big believer in that.
Interesting.
Why is it challenging?
Well, if I look at the more traditional crypto
and corporate investment, like, there's
a new investment that's being deployed, finally in 2004,
but all the money is only going to early stage and seed stage
companies.
There's no money going in follow-on series A, B, C, D,
and so on.
And actually, all the actors right now,
like the one that killed, killed, survived,
they might need, at some point, a more cash injection
before they do go back to more acquisition.
So that's one thing that's missing.
The second is, like, we've seen the ride over the past year
or two years of a lot of new ecosystem, blockchain
ecosystem, sweet, abtose, our volunteer table, and so on.
Those are, like, deploying cash and grants
for developers to join.
So we are still in this phase of, like, everyone
is going to fight, capture, like, the best application,
the best services.
True as well, probably you can talk more about it.
And not in, like, OK, now there are some dead PCs
and only the tech team remaining,
and it's time for M&A to consolidate.
I mean, there is a point where, today, there is more chains
than there is the app that are successful.
And that's a problem.
And it's 100 times easier to raise money
for an infrastructure than it is for ADAP, which is fair,
because it's actually much difficult to be successful
creating ADAP that an infrastructure.
And that's a problem.
So it's coming, but I don't know if he's here.
Yeah, I'm not going to see him.
So guys, we're going to go on to the far round of questions.
The bell is here.
Now we're going to use them for rapid questions, right?
So I'm going to ask questions.
I want one or two word answers.
And we're going to get a rock and roll the bell is here
to keep us honest.
You guys ready?
Yes.
What is the region in the world you're
the most bullish about crypto for the year ahead?
Alex.
Two words, not US.
A lot of anti-US sentiment in the room, Justin.
What region are the most bullish?
Dubai and Hong Kong.
Here we go.
Sebastian.
Hong Kong and Asia.
Hong Kong and Asia, interesting.
We're in Dubai here.
What's your favorite thing about Dubai?
Sebastian.
It's a great, both financial and controlled
up that connect three major continent, Europe, Africa,
and Asia.
Beautiful.
Favorite thing about Dubai, Justin?
I believe here is a mix of culture.
So we can see all people from all around the globe come to Dubai.
I think Dubai is not only a crypto hub, but also a culture
hub in the region.
Yeah, absolutely.
Alex, favorite.
Two words, French restaurants.
French restaurants.
Share one.
OK, if you could go back to school today,
what is the one class you would take
that you wish you had taken back in the day?
Alex.
Chinese.
Justin, what's your favorite course?
Come here.
What's your favorite course?
What's course you wish you had taken university?
Computer science?
Computer science.
Sebastian, what course you would take?
I took computer science, but I think I would network
and engineering, but I would go even further into data science
and anything touching to AI.
It's such a basic, elementary thing you need to have now.
And financial aid, there is, as well.
Fortunately, we don't teach it enough in France, mostly
in Europe, and only a few part of the world,
like people are learning early on.
This is a controversial one.
I'm starting with you, Sebastian.
If you could hold one coin, it could not be signed,
it could not be thrown.
You can hold one coin for the next day, not Chile's either.
It cannot be signed.
What is one coin you can hold for the next 10 years?
If you're not allowed to sell, what coin do you hold?
Sebastian.
It cannot be signed.
It could be a--
Mine, signed.
No, no, you're not allowed, Simon.
Yeah, if.
Still.
If.
Ah, if you're a--
If you're a--
Sorry, I was not able to--
OK, Justin.
Bitcoin.
Alex?
Non-financial advice.
OK, this is another one.
I'm starting from you, Alex.
If you could launch tomorrow a new crypto startup,
and you can choose any existing CEO of crypto company,
who would you choose as your co-founder?
I don't know.
As a co-founder, I love to say this.
He's a hustler.
No, actually, no.
I'll take Yat.
He's Yat.
He took the Yat and Zeb from Animoca.
Yes, Zeb.
They were traveling the world like you never seen that.
And it's actually very valuable.
So, Yat Zeb, Animoca.
Justin, who would you choose as your new co-founder?
C-D.
C-Z.
Here we go.
Sebastian, who's your new co-founder?
Who do you choose, if you can?
So, I've been together with a co-founder after Madrid
for 16 years.
I think we don't need to change the recipes at works.
Yeah, exactly.
Very good.
Very impressive, by the way.
Launching you start with the new one.
That's the answer.
This is a special one.
I'm starting with you, Sebastian.
Sam Bankman-Feed gives you a phone call from prison.
What do you tell him?
That's exciting.
What?
Sandbag, if you call--
S-B-F gives you a call.
He's calling you what you tell him.
Do you have any regrets?
Any regrets?
Justin, what do you tell us, B.F.?
Oh.
Why you do that?
[LAUGHTER]
Alex.
Oh, no, for fuck's sake.
I hope they have a good haircut hair dresser there.
[LAUGHTER]
And last question, guys.
The typical tradition of river cows
all staged with me to finish off token 24/9,
Dubai the 2024 edition.
Alex, I'm starting with you.
If you could have lunch or dinner with one person dead or alive.
You could have lunch or dinner with one person dead or alive.
Who would you have lunch or dinner with?
Steve Jobs.
Justin, who would you have lunch or dinner with?
Warren Buffett.
[LAUGHTER]
If only that was available.
And Sebastian, to close after conference,
wait if you could buy lunch or dinner.
You could have lunch or dinner one person dead or alive.
Who would you have lunch with?
Bill Gates.
My god.
Here we go.
Ladies and gentlemen, a big hands up plus for the panel.
That was the end for the show, guys.
Thank you very much, everybody.
[MUSIC PLAYING]